<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Catechisme of Christian religion.</title>
            <title>Heidelberger Katechismus.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13031.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S92905</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">56572852</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 56572852</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180955</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00148)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180955)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2147:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Catechisme of Christian religion.</title>
                  <title>Heidelberger Katechismus.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Schilders, Printer to the States of Zealand.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Middelborough, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Page numbers 93-138 are written in manuscript at the head of each page.</note>
                  <note>Title page ornament.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Heidelberger Katechismus --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180955:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180955:1"/>
            <p>A CATECHISME OF CHRISTIAN RELIGION.</p>
            <p>AT MIDDELBOROUGH, By Richard Schilders, Printer to the States of Zealand. 1610.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:180955:2"/>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:180955:2"/>
            <head>A CATECHISME OF CHRISTIAN RELIGION.</head>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday </seg>Firſt</label> Queſtion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What is thy only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in life &amp; death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat both in ſoule &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.19.</note>, whether I live or die,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 14.8.</note> I am not mine own, but belong<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.28.</note> wholy vnto my moſt faithful Lord &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior Ieſus Chriſt who by his precious blood moſt fully ſatisfying<note n="d" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.18.</note> for my ſinnes, hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<note n="e" place="margin">1 Iohn 3.8.</note> me from all the power of the Devil, and ſo preſerveth<note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 6.39.</note> me, that without the will of my heavenly Father, not ſo much as a haire may fall<note n="g" place="margin">Mar 10.30. Luc 21 19</note> from my head: yea all things muſt<note n="h" place="margin">Rom 8.28.</note> ſerve for my ſafetie. Wherefore by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit alſo he aſſureth<note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.22.</note> me of everlaſting life, &amp; maketh<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 8 24.</note> me ready, &amp; prepared, that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth I may live to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Queſt. <hi>How many things are neceſſarie for thee to know, that thou enioying this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, maist live and die happily?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Three<note n="l" place="margin">Luke 24. Tit. 3.3 &amp;c.</note>. The firſt, what is the<note n="m" place="margin">Iohn 9.42 Rom. 3.10.</note> great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of my ſinne &amp; miſerie. The ſecond, how I am delivered<note n="n" place="margin">Iohn 17.3</note> from all ſinne and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. The third, what thankes I owe<note n="o" place="margin">Ephe. 5.10</note> vnto God for this deliverie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:180955:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE FIRST PART, OF THE MISERIE OF MAN.</head>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>2</label> 3. Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whence knowest thou thy miſerie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of the law of God<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 3.20.</note>.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Queſt. <hi>What doth the law of God require of vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That doeth Chriſt ſummarilie teach vs, Mat. 22.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with al thy heart, with all thy ſoule, with all thy minde, and with all thy ſtrength<note n="b" place="margin">Luke 10.17</note>. This is the firſt and the great command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the ſecond is like to this: Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf. On theſe two commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hangeth the whole Law and the Prophetes.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>3</label> 5. Queſt. <hi>Art thou able to keepe all theſe things perfectly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No truely<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 5.1. 1 Iohn 1.8.</note>: For by nature I am prone to the hatred of God &amp; of my neighbour<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.7. Ephe. 2.3.</note>.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Queſt. <hi>Did God then make man ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and perverſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Not ſo<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 1.31.</note>: but rather he made him good and to his own image<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 1.26.</note>, that is, endued with true righteouſnes &amp; holines, that he might rightly know God his Creator, and hartily love him, &amp; live with him bleſſed for ever, and that to laude and magnifie him<note n="g" place="margin">2. Cor. 3.18 4.5. Col. 3.10. Ephe. 1.6.</note>.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Queſt. <hi>Whence then ariſeth this wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mans nature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> From the fall and diſobedience of our
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:180955:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>firſt parents, Adam and Eve<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 5.6. Rom. 6.21.</note>: hence is our nature ſo corrupt, that we are all conceaved and borne in ſinne<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 51.4. Gen. 5.3.8.6.5.</note>.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Queſt. <hi>Are we ſo corrupt, that we are not at all apt to do well, and are prone to all vice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In deed we are: except we be regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the holy Ghoſt<note n="k" place="margin">Iohn 3.5. Rom. 15. Iob. 10.4. &amp;c.</note>.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sund. </seg>4</label> 9. Queſt. <hi>Doth not God then iniurie to man, who in the Law requireth that of him, which he is not able to performe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No<note n="l" place="margin">Iohn 3.5. Ephe. 4.24. Colo. 3.10.</note>. For God had made man ſuch a one, as he might perfourme it: But man, by the impulſion of the Devill<note n="m" place="margin">Luke 10.30</note>, and his owne ſtubburneſſe, bereaved him ſelfe and all his poſteritie of thoſe Divine graces.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Queſt. <hi>Doth God leave this ſtubburneſſe and falling away of man vnpuniſhed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No: but is angrie in moſt dreadfull manner<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 5.12. Heb. 9.27.</note>, as well for the ſinnes wherein we are borne, as alſo for thoſe which our ſelves commit, and in moſt iuſt iudgement pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth them with preſent &amp; everlaſting pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, as him ſelfe pronounceth: <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be he that performeth not all the wordes of the Law to doe them</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Deut. 27.24 Gal. 3.10.</note>.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Queſt. <hi>Is not God therefore mercifull?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yea verely, he is mercifull<note n="p" place="margin">Exod. 34.6.</note> but ſo, that he is alſo iuſt<note n="q" place="margin">Exod. 20.5. 2. Cor. 6.14.</note> Wherefore his iuſtice requireth, that the ſame which is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:180955:4"/>againſt the Divine Maieſtie of God: ſhould alſo be recompenced with extreme, that is, everlaſting puniſhmentes both of body and ſoule.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>THE SECOND PART, OF MANS DELIVERY.</head>
            <p n="12">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday </seg>5</label> 12. Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seeing then by the iust iudgement of God, we are ſubiect both to temporall, and eternall puniſhments; is there yet any meanes or way remayning, whereby wee may bee delivered from theſe puniſhmentes, and bee reconciled to God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwere.</p>
            <p>GOD will have his iuſtice<note n="a" place="margin">Exod 20 5</note> ſatisfied: wherefore it is neceſſarie, that<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 8 3</note> wee ſatisfie, either by our ſelves, or by an other.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Are we able to ſatisfie by our ſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Nor a whit. Nay rather we doe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day<note n="c" place="margin">Iob 9 2, 3. and 15.15. Mat. 6.12.</note> increaſe our debt.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Queſt. <hi>Js there any creature able in heaven or in earth, which is only a creature, to ſatisfie for vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> None. For firſt, God will not<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh that ſinne in any other creature, which man hath committed. And further, neither
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:180955:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>can that which is nothing, but a creature, ſuſtaine the wrath of God againſt ſinne, and<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 130: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> deliver others from it.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Queſt. <hi>What maner of Mediator then and deliver must we ſeeke for?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Such a one verily, as is very man, &amp; perfectly iuſt, and yet in power aboue all creatures, that is, who alſo is verie<note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.14. Heb. 7.16. Eſa. 7.25.</note> God.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Queſt. <hi>Wherefore is it neceſſarie that he be verie man, and perfectly iust too?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe the iuſtice of God requireth that the ſame humane nature whiche hath ſinned, doe it ſelfe likewiſe make reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence for ſinne: But he<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> that is him ſelf a ſinner<note n="h" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18.</note>, can not make recompence for others.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Queſt. <hi>Why must he alſo be very God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That he might by the power of his Godhead<note n="i" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18. Iſa. 55.3.</note> ſuſtaine in his fleſh the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Gods wrath, and<note n="k" place="margin">1 Iohn 2. Act. 20.28.</note> might recover and reſtore vnto vs that righteouſnes and life which we loſt.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Queſt. <hi>And who is that Mediator, which is togither both very God, and a very perfect iust man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Even our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 1.23. 1 Tim. 3.16. Luke 2.11.</note> who is made to vs of God wiſedome, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſanctification, and<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 1.2. Heb. 1.1.</note> redemption.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Queſt. <hi>Whence knowest thou this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Out of the Goſpell, which God
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:180955:5"/>firſt made knowen in<note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> Paradiſe, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes<note n="n" place="margin">Gen 22.18. Rom. 1.2. Heb. 1.1.</note> did ſpreed it abroad by the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes and Prophetes<note n="o" place="margin">Iohn 5.46. Heb. 10.7.</note>: ſhadowed it by ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices &amp; other ceremonies of the law: &amp; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="p" place="margin">Rom 10.4. Heb. 13.8.</note> acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed it by his only begotten Son.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday </seg>7</label> 20. Queſt. <hi>Is then ſalvation restored by Christ to all men, who periſhed in Adam?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not to all: but to thoſe onely, who by a true faith are engraffed into him,<note n="q" place="margin">Iohn 1.12. Rom. 11.20. Heb. 10.39.</note> and receave his benefites.</p>
            <p n="21">21. Queſt. <hi>What is faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is not only a knowledge, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I ſurely aſſent to all thinges which God hath<note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 11.13. Iſa 2.19.</note> revealed vnto vs in his word, but alſo an aſſured<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 4.16. Iac. 1.8.</note> truſt kindled in my<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 1.16. 1 Cor. 1.21. Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 16.14.</note> heart by the holy<note n="v" place="margin">Mat. 16.17 Iohn 3 5. Phil. 1.19.</note> ghoſt through the Goſpell, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I make my repoſe in God, being aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie reſolved, that remiſſion of ſinnes, everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting righteouſnes and life<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 9.2. Rom. 5.1.</note> is given not to others onely, but to me alſo, and that freelie through the mercie of God, for the<note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> merite of Chriſt alone.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Queſt. <hi>What are thoſe things which are neceſſarie for a Chriſtian man to beleeve?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All thinges whiche are<note n="z" place="margin">Iohn 20.31 Mat. 28.10.</note> promiſed vs in the Goſpell: the ſumme whereof is briefly compriſed in the Creed of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, or in the Articles of the Catholike and vndoubted faith of all Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:180955:5"/> 23. Queſt. <hi>Which is the Creede?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Beleeue in God the Father almighty, maker of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth. And in Ieſus Chriſt his only Sonne our Lord: which was conceived by the holy Ghoſt: borne of the virgine Mary: ſuffered vnder Pontius Pilate: was crucified, dead and buried: he deſcended into hell: the third day he roſe againe from the dead: he aſcended into heaven, and ſitteth at the right hand of God the Father almightie: from thence ſhall hee come to iudge the quicke and the dead. I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt: the holy Catholike Church: the communion of Saints: the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes: the reſurrection of the body, and the life everlaſting. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MEN.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>8</label> 24. Queſt. <hi>Into how many partes is this Creede divided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Into three parts. The firſt is, of the eternall Father and our Creation. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, of the Sonne and our Redemption. The third, of the holy Ghoſt and our Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Queſt. <hi>Seeing there is but one only ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God, why namest thou theſe three, The Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghost?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe God hath ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 1.26. Eſa. 1.1. Mat. 3.16.</note> manifeſted him ſelfe in his word, that theſe three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinct perſons are that one true, everlaſting God.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>OF THE FATHER.</head>
               <p n="26">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>9</label> 26. Queſt. <hi>What beleeveſt thou, when thou ſaiest, I beleeue in God the Father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, maker of heaven and earth?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:180955:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I beleeve the everlaſting Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who<note n="a" place="margin">Gene. 1. &amp; 2 Pſal. 33.6.</note> hath made of nothing heaven and earth, with all that are in them, who likewiſe vpholdeth and<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal 134.3. Mat 10.29. Heb. 1.3</note> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneth the ſame by his eternall Counſel &amp; providence;<note n="c" place="margin">Iohn 1.12 Rom. 8.15 Gal. 4 5 Ephe. 1. y.</note> to be my God and my Father for Chriſtes ſake: and therfore I do ſo truſt in him, and ſo relie on him, that I may not doubt, but he will provide all thinges<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 55.23 Mat. 6.26.</note> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie both for my ſoule and body. And further, whatſoever evils he ſendeth on me in this troubleſome life, he wil<note n="e" place="margin">Rom 8.28</note> turne them to my ſafetie, ſeeing both he is able to do it, as beeing<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 10.12.</note> God almightie, and willing to do it, as being<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 6, &amp;c.</note> a bountifull father.</p>
               <p n="27">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sund. </seg>10</label> 27. Queſt. <hi>What is the providence of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The almightie power of God eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie where preſent,<note n="h" place="margin">Acts 17.25</note> whereby he doeth as it were with his hande vpholde and<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> governe heaven &amp; earth, with all the creatures ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: So that thoſe things which grow in the earth, as likewiſe raine and drought, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes and barraines, meate and<note n="k" place="margin">Iere 5.24 Act. 14.17.</note> drinke,<note n="l" place="margin">Iohn 9 3.</note> health and ſickenes,<note n="m" place="margin">Prov. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.7.8.11.</note> riches and poverty, in a word, all things come not raſhly or by chance, but by his fatherlie counſell and will.</p>
               <p n="28">28. Queſt. <hi>What doeth this knowledge of the Creation &amp; providence of God profit vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:180955:6"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That in adverſitie<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 5.3 Iac. 1.3.</note> we may be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and<note n="o" place="margin">Deut. 8.10 1 Theſ. 5.</note> thankfull in proſperitie, and<note n="p" place="margin">Rom 5.4</note> have hereafter our chiefeſt hope repoſed in God our moſt faithfull father, being ſure that there is nothing whiche may<note n="q" place="margin">Iohn 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw vs from his love, for as much as all creatures are ſo in his power, that without his will they are not<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 8.38</note> able not only to doe anie thing, but not ſo much as once to moove.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>OF THE SONNE.</head>
               <p n="29">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sund. </seg>11</label> 29. Queſt. <hi>Why is the Sonne of God called Ieſus, that is, a Saviour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe he ſaveth vs from all our<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 1.21 Luke 1.31.</note> ſinnes: Neither ought any ſafetie to bee ſought for from any other, nor<note n="b" place="margin">Acts 4.12</note> can elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where be found.</p>
               <p n="30">30. Queſt. <hi>Doe they then beleeve in the only ſaviour Ieſus, who ſeeke for happines and ſafetie of the Saintes, or of them ſelves, or elſ-where?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No. For although in word they boaſt them ſelves of him as their Saviour, yet in deed they denie the onely Saviour<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.13 Gal. 5.4</note> Ieſus. For it muſt needes be that either Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is not a perfect Saviour, or that they who embrace him as their Saviour with a true faith, poſſeſſe all things in him, which<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 12.2 Iſa. 9.6.7.</note> are required vnto ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="31">
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:180955:7"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>12</label> 31. Queſt. <hi>Why is he called Christ, that is annointed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe he was ordained of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and annointed of the holy Ghoſt, the<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 45.8. Heb. 1.9.</note> chief Prophet and<note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 1.18. and 15.15.</note> Doctour: who hath<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 11.27. Pſal. 110.4. Heb. 7.21.1</note> opened vnto vs the ſecrete counſaile and all the wil of his father concerning our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: And the High-Prieſt, who with that one onely ſacrifice of his body, hath<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 8.34.</note> redeemed vs, and doth continuallie make interceſſion to his father for vs. And a<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 2.6. Luke 1.33.</note> king, who ruleth vs by his woord and ſpirit, and defendeth and<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 28.18. Iohn 10.28.</note> maintaineth that ſalvation which he hath purchaſed for vs.</p>
               <p n="32">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>13</label> 32. Queſt. <hi>But why art thou called a Christian?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe through faith I am a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of<note n="l" place="margin">Acts 11.26. 1 Cor. 6.15.</note> Ieſus Chriſt, and partaker<note n="m" place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.27 Ioel 2.28.</note> of his annointing, that both I may<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 10.33.</note> confeſſe his name, and preſent my ſelfe vnto him a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 12.1. Apoc. 4.8.</note> ſacrifice of thankefulneſſe, and alſo may in this life fight againſt ſinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than with a free and good conſcience, and afterward<note n="p" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.18.19.</note> enioye an everlaſting kingdome with Chriſt over all creatures.</p>
               <p n="33">33. Queſt. <hi>For what cauſe is Christ called the only begotten ſonne of God, when we alſo are the ſonnes of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt alone is the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:180955:7"/>coeternall and naturall ſonne of the eternall<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 1.14. Heb. 1.2.</note> father, and we<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 8.5. Ephe. 1.6.</note> are but ſonnes adopted of the father by grace for his ſake.</p>
               <p n="34">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>14</label> 34. Queſt. <hi>Wherefore callest thou him our Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe he redeeming &amp; ranſoming both our body and ſoule from ſinnes, not with gold nor ſilver, but with his precious blood, and delivering vs from all the power of the Devill, hath ſet vs<note n="c" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.18. 1 Cor. 6.20.</note> free to ſerve him.</p>
               <p n="35">35. Queſt. <hi>What beleevest thou, when thou ſaist, he was conceaved by the holy Ghost, &amp; borne of the Virgine Marie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That the ſonne of God, who<note n="d" place="margin">Iohn 1.1. Col. 1.15.</note> is &amp; continueth true &amp; everlaſting<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 9.5. 1 Iohn 5.20.</note> God,<note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 1.14. Gala. 4.4.</note> tooke the verie nature of man, of the fleſhe<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 1.18. Luke 1.35.</note> and blood of the Virgin Marie, by the working of the holy Ghoſt,<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 132.11 Act. 2.30. &amp;c Rom. 1.3.</note> that withall hee might bee the true ſeede of David,<note n="i" place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> like vnto his brethren in all things,<note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> ſinne excepted.</p>
               <p n="36">36. Queſt. <hi>What profit takest thou, by Christes holy conception and nativitie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That he is our<note n="l" place="margin">Ha. 2.16.17.</note> Mediator, and doth cover with his innocencie and perfect ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe my ſinnes, in which I was concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that they may not come in the ſight of<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 32.1. 1 Cor. 1.30 Rom. 8.34.</note> God.</p>
               <p n="37">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>15</label> 37. Queſt. <hi>What beleeveſt thou, when thou ſaist, he ſuffered?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:180955:8"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That he, all the time of his life, which he led in the earth, but eſpecially at the ende thereof,<note n="“" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.24 Iſa 53.12.</note> ſuſteined the wrath of God, both in body &amp; ſoule, againſt the ſin of all mankind, that he might by his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the only<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 2 2. Rom. 3.25.</note> propitiatorie Sacrifice, deliver our body and ſoule from everlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and purchaſe vnto vs the favour of God, righteouſnes, and everlaſting life.</p>
               <p n="38">38. Queſt. <hi>For what cauſe ſhould he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vnder Pilate, as being his iudge?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That he being innocent and<note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 23.14 Iohn 19.4.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned before a civill iudge, might<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 69.4 Gal 3:13</note> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vs from the ſevere iudgement of God, which remained for all men.</p>
               <p n="39">39. Queſt. <hi>But is there any thing more in it, that he was faſtned to the croſſe, than if hee had ſuffered any other kinde of death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is more: For by this I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that he tooke vpon him ſelfe the curſe which did ly on me. For the death of the croſſe was<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 21. Gal. 3.13.</note> accurſed of God.</p>
               <p n="40">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sund. </seg>16</label> 40. Queſt. <hi>Why was it neceſſarie for Chriſt to humble himſelfe vnto death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ</hi> Becauſe the iuſtice and trueth of God could by no<note n="d" place="margin">Gene. 2.71.</note> other meanes be ſatisfied for our ſinnes, but by the very death of the<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 2.9. Phil. 2.18.</note> ſonne of God.</p>
               <p n="41">41. Queſt. <hi>To what end was he buried alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:180955:8"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That thereby he might make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that he was<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 13.29. Iohn 19.38.</note> dead in deed.</p>
               <p n="42">42. Queſt. <hi>But ſince that Christ died for vs, why must we alſo dye?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Our death is not a ſatisfaction for our ſinnes, but the aboliſhing of ſinne, and our paſſage into<note n="g" place="margin">Iohn 5.24. Phil. 1.23</note> everlaſting life.</p>
               <p n="43">43 Queſt. <hi>What other commoditie receyve we by the ſacrifice and death of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That by the vertue of his death, our old man is crucified, ſlaine, and<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 6.7</note> buried togither with them, that hencefoorth evill luſtes and deſires may not<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note> raigne in vs, but wee may<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> offer our ſelves vnto him a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of thankeſgiving.</p>
               <p n="44">44. Queſt. <hi>Why is there added, Hee deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into hell?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That in my greateſt paines, &amp; moſt grievous tentations, I may ſupport my ſelfe with this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, that my Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath deliuered<note n="*" place="margin">Eſa. 53.10 Mat. 27.46.</note> mee, by the vnſpeakeable diſtreſſes, torments and terrors of his ſoule, into which he was plunged both before, and then eſpeciallie, when hee hanged on the croſſe, from the ſtraites and torments of hel.</p>
               <p n="45">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sund. </seg>17</label> 45. Queſt. <hi>What doeth the reſurrection of Christ profite vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, by his Reſurrection he van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed death, that he might<note n="“" place="margin">1. Cor. 15 16. &amp; 54.55.</note> make vs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:180955:9"/>of that righteouſneſſe, which he had gotten vs by his death. Againe we are now alſo<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.4. Col. 3.1. &amp;c.</note> ſtirred vp by his power to a new life. Laſtly, the reſurrection of our head Chriſt, is a<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. Rom. 8.11.</note> pledge vnto vs of our glorious reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
               <p n="46">46. Queſt. <hi>How vnderstand you that, He aſcended into heaven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That Chriſt, his Diſciples looking on, was<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 1.9. Mar. 16.19.</note> taken vp from the earth into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and yet ſtill<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 4.14. Rom. 8.34. Ephe. 4.10.</note> is there for our ſakes, and will be, vntill he come againe to iudge the quicke and dead.</p>
               <p n="47">47. Queſt.<note place="margin">Mat. 28.20</note> 
                  <hi>Is not Christ with vs then vntill the end of the world as he hath promiſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Chriſt is true God, and true man: and ſo according to his manhoode, he is not now on earth: but according to his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, his maieſtie, his grace, and ſpirit, hee is at no time from vs.</p>
               <p n="48">48. Queſt. <hi>Are not by this meanes the two natures in Christ pulled aſunder, if his humanitie be not whereſoever his divinitie is?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> No: for ſeeing his divinitie is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, and every where<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 1.11. Ma. 24.30.</note> preſent: it followeth neceſſarily that<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 28.20 Iohn 16.18. &amp; 17.11.</note> the ſame is without the bounds of his humane nature which he tooke to him, and yet is neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in it and abideth perſonally vnited to it.</p>
               <p n="49">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:180955:9"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>18</label> 49. Queſt. <hi>What fruit doth the aſcenſion of Christ into heaven bring vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. Firſt, that he<note n="*" place="margin">Heb 7.14. 1 Iohn 2.3. Rom. 8.34.</note> maketh interceſſion to his Father in heaven for vs. Next, that we haue our fleſh in heaven, that we may be confirmed thereby, as by a ſure pledge, that it ſhall come to paſſe, that hee who is our head, will<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 14.2. Ephe. 2.6.</note> lift vp vs his members vnto him. Thirdly, that hee<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 14.16. 2 Cor. 1.22. 1 Cor. 5.5.</note> ſendeth vs his ſpirit in ſteed of a pledge betweene him and vs, by whoſe forcible working we ſeeke after, not earthly, but heavenly things, where he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is ſitting at the right hand of God<note n="c" place="margin">Col 3.1. Phil. 3.20.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="50">50. Queſt. <hi>Why is it further ſaid, Hee ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt therefore is aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into heaven, to<note n="d" place="margin">Ephe. 1.20. Col. 1.18.</note> ſhewe there that he is the head of the Church, by whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 28.18. Iohn 5.22.</note> governeth all things.</p>
               <p n="51">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>19</label> 51. Queſt. <hi>What profit is this glory of our head Christ vnto vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, that through his holy ſpirit, he<note n="f" place="margin">Ephe. 4.10.</note> poureth vpon vs his members, heavenly graces. Then, that he ſhieldeth and<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 2.9. Rom. 8.23. Phil. 3.20.</note> defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs by his power againſt all our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p n="52">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>19</label> 52. Queſt. <hi>What comfort hast thou by the comming againe of Christ to iudge the quick and the dead?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:180955:10"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That in all my miſeries and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions,<note n="h" place="margin">Luk 21.28. Rom. 8.23.24 Phil. 3.20.</note> I looke, with my head lifted vp, for the very ſame, who before yeelded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto the iudgement of God for me, &amp;<note n="i" place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.6.7 Mat. 25.41.</note> tooke away all malediction from me, to come iudge from heaven, to throw all his and my enemies into everlaſting paines, but to<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 25.34.</note> tranſlate me with all his choſen, vnto him ſelfe, into celeſtiall ioyes, and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting glorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>OF THE HOLY GHOST.</head>
               <p n="53">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>20</label> 53. Queſt. <hi>What beleevest thou concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the holy ghost?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, that he is true and coeternall God with the eternall father &amp; the<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1.2. Iſa. 48.16. 1 Cor. 3.16.</note> ſonne: Secondly, that he is alſo<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 28.19 2 Cor. 1.2.</note> given vnto me to<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 3.14. 1 Pet. 1.2.</note> make me through a true faith, partaker of Chriſt and all his benefites, to<note n="d" place="margin">Acts 9.31.</note> comfort me, and to<note n="e" place="margin">Iohn 16. 1 Pet. 4.14.</note> abide with me for ever.</p>
               <p n="54">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sun. </seg>21</label> 54. Queſt. <hi>What beleevest thou concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the holy &amp; catholike Church of Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I beleeve that the ſonne of<note n="f" place="margin">Iho. 10.11.</note> God doeth from<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 26.4.</note> the beginning of the worlde<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 8.29. Ephe. 1.10.</note> to the end, gather, defend and<note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 59.21.</note> preſerve vnto him ſelfe by his ſpirit, and<note n="k" place="margin">Act. 2.46.</note> word out of whole mankind,<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> a company<note n="m" place="margin">1 Iohn 3.21</note> choſen to everlaſting life, &amp; agreeing in true faith: and that I am a lively<note n="n" place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.19.</note> member of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and ſo ſhall<note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 8 9. Rom. 8.35.</note> remaine for ever.</p>
               <p n="55">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:180955:10"/> 55. Queſt. <hi>What meane theſe words, The communion of Saints?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, that all and everie one, who beleeveth, are in common<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 1.3. Rom. 8.32. 1 Cor. 12.13.</note> partakers of Chriſt, and all his graces, as being his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. And then, that every one ought readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.5. Phil. 2.4.5.6.</note> cheerfully to beſtow the giftes and graces which they have received, to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon commoditie and ſafetie of all.</p>
               <p n="56">56. Queſt. <hi>What beleevest thou concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning remiſſion of ſinnes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That God, for the ſatisfaction made by<note n="c" place="margin">1 Iohn 2.2. 2 Cor. 5.19.</note> Chriſt, hath put out all the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance<note n="d" place="margin">Iere. 32.34. Pſal. 103.3. Rom. 8.1.2.3</note> of my ſinnes, and alſo of that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption within me, wherewith I muſt fight all my life time: and doeth freely endow me with the righteouſnes of Chriſt, that<note n="e" place="margin">Iohn. 3.18.</note> I come not at any time into iudgement.</p>
               <p n="57">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>22</label> 57. Queſt. <hi>What comfort haſt thou, by the reſurrection of the fleſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That not only my ſoule, after it ſhall depart out of my body, ſhall preſently bee taken<note n="f" place="margin">Luke 23.4. Phil. 1.23.</note> vp to Chriſt, but that this my fleſh alſo, beeing raiſed vp by the power of Chriſt, ſhall be againe vnited to my ſoule, and ſhall be<note n="g" place="margin">1. Cor. 15. Iob 19.25.</note> made like to the glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="58">58. Queſt. <hi>What comfort takest thou of the article of everlasting life?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:180955:11"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That for as much as<note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor 5.2.3</note> I feele alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in my hart the beginning of everlaſting life, it<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9. Iohn 17.37.</note> ſhall at length come to paſſe, that after this life I ſhall enioye full and perfect bliſſe, wherein I may magnifie God forever; which bleſſednes verily, neither eie hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, neither hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie man in thought conceived it.</p>
               <p n="59">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>23</label> 59. Queſt. <hi>But when thou beleeveſt all theſe thinges, what profit redoundeth thence vnto thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That I am righteous in Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, an an heire of eternall life<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 2.4. Rom. 1.17. Iohn 3.36.</note>.</p>
               <p n="60">60. Que. <hi>How art thou righteous before God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Only<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 3.21. &amp;c Gal 2.16 Ephe. 2.8, 9.</note> by faith in Chriſt Ieſus: ſo that, although my conſcience accuſe mee, that I have grievouſlie treſpaſſed againſt all the commaundements of God, &amp; have not<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 3.9. &amp;c.</note> kept one of them: and further, am as yet<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 7.23</note> prone to all evill: yet notwithſtanding (if I<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 3.42. Iohn 3.18.</note> embrace theſe benefites of Chriſt with a true confidence and perſwaſion of minde, the ful and<note n="h" place="margin">Tit. 3.5 Ephe. 2.8.9.</note> perfect ſatisfaction, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and holines of Chriſt, without any<note n="i" place="margin">Iohn 2.2.</note> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of mine, of the meere<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 3.24. Deut. 9.6.</note> mercie of God, is<note n="l" place="margin">Iohn 2.1.</note> imputed and<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 4.4. 2 Cor. 5.19.</note> given vnto me, and that ſo as if neither I had committed any ſinne, neither any corruption did ſticke vnto me yea as I my ſelfe had perfectly<note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.21.</note> accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:180955:11"/>that obedience, which Chriſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed for me.</p>
               <p n="61">61. Queſt. <hi>Why affirmeſt thou, that thou art made righteous by faith only?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not for that I pleaſe God through the worthines of meere faith: but becauſe only the ſatisfaction, righteouſnes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of Chriſt is my righteouſnes before<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.33. 1 Cor. 2.2.</note> God: and I cannot take hold of it<note n="“" place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.10.</note> or apply it vnto my ſelf any other way than by faith.</p>
               <p n="62">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>24</label> 62. Queſt. <hi>Why cannot our good workes bee righteouſnes, or ſome part of righteouſnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe that righteouſnes whiche muſt ſtande faſte before the iudgement of God, muſt be in al points perfect, &amp;<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 3.10. Deut. 27.26.</note> agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Law of God. Now our workes, even the beſt of them, are imperfect in this life, and<note n="b" place="margin">Eſa. 64.</note> defiled with ſinne.</p>
               <p n="63">63. Queſt. <hi>How is it that our good workes merit nothing, ſeeing God promiſeth that hee will give a rewarde for them, both in this life, and in the life to come?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That reward is not given of merit, but of<note n="c" place="margin">Luke 17.10.</note> grace.</p>
               <p n="64">64. Queſt. <hi>But doeth not this doctrine make men careles and profane?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> No: For neither can it be, but they, which are incorporated into Chriſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:180955:12"/>faith, ſhould bring forth the fruites of<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 7.18. Iohn 15.5.</note> thankefulnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>OF THE SACRAMENTS.</head>
               <p n="65">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>25</label> 65. Queſt. <hi>Seeing then that only faith ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs partakers of Christ and his benefits, whence doeth it proceede?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> From the holy ghoſt, who<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 28. and 6.23. Phil. 1.29.</note> kindleth it in our hearts by the preaching of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 28.19. 2 Pet. 1.22.</note> confirmeth it by the vſe of the Sacraments.</p>
               <p n="66">66. Queſt. <hi>What are the Sacraments?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> They are ſacred ſignes and ſeales ſet before our eyes, &amp; ordeined of God for this cauſe, that he may declare &amp; ſeale by them the promiſe of his Goſpell vnto vs, to wit, that he giveth freely remiſſion of ſinnes, &amp;<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 17.11. Rom. 4.11. Deut. 30.6. Levi. 6.25. Iſa. 6.6.</note> life everlaſting not only to all in generall, but to every one in particular that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, for that only ſacrifice of Chriſt which he accompliſhed vpon the croſſe.</p>
               <p n="67">67. Queſt. <hi>Doe not then both the word and ſacraments tende to that ende, as to lead our faith vnto the ſacrifice of Christ finiſhed on the croſſe, as to the only grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of our ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is even ſo. For the holy ghoſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs by the goſpell, &amp; aſſureth vs by the Sacraments, that the ſalvation of all of vs, ſtandeth in the holy ſacrifice of Chriſt<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 6.3. Gal. 3.27.</note> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for vs vpon the croſſe.</p>
               <p n="68">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:180955:12"/> 68. Queſt. <hi>How many Sacramentes hath Christ ordeined in the new Testament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Two. Baptiſme, &amp; the Lords Supper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>OF BAPTISME.</head>
               <p n="69">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>26</label> 69. Queſt. <hi>How art thou admoniſhed and aſſured in Baptiſme, that thou art partaker of the only ſacrifice of Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 28.19. Acts 2.38.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward waſhing of water, adioyning this<note n="b" place="margin">Mar. 16.16. Mat. 3.11. Rom. 6.3.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe therevnto, that I am no leſſe aſſuredly waſhed by his blood and ſpirit from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſſe of my ſoule, that is, from all my ſinnes, than I am<note n="c" place="margin">Mar. 1.14. Luc. 3.3.</note> waſhed outwardly with water, whereby all the filthineſſe of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die vſeth to be purged.</p>
               <p n="70">70. Queſt. <hi>What is it to bee waſhed with the blood and ſpirit of Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is to receive of God forgivenes of ſins freely for the blood of Chriſt, which he<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 12.24. 1 Pet. 1.2. Apoc. 1.5.</note> ſhed for vs in his Sacrifice on, the croſſe. And alſo to be renued by the holy Ghoſt, &amp; through his ſanctifying of vs, to become members of Chriſt, that we may more and more die to ſinne, and<note n="e" place="margin">Iohn 1.33. Rom. 6.4. Col. 2.12.</note> live holy and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blame.</p>
               <p n="71">71. Queſt. <hi>Where doeth Christ promiſe vs that hee will as certainly waſh vs with his blood and ſpirit, as we are waſhed with the water of baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:180955:13"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the inſtitution of Baptiſme; the words whereof are theſe:<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Goe and teach all Nations, Baptiſing them in the name of the father, the ſonne, and the holy Ghost,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 16.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that ſhall beleve &amp; be baptiſed, ſhalbe ſaved: but he that will not beleeve, ſhalbe damned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This promiſe is repeated again, whereas the ſcripture calleth Baptiſme, the<note n="h" place="margin">Tit. 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>waſhing of the new bith, and</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 22.16.</note> 
                  <hi>forgiveneſſe of ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="72">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>27</label> 72.Queſt. <hi>Is then the outward Baptiſme of water the waſhing away of ſinnes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is not. For the<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 3.11. 1 Pet. 3.11.</note> blood of Chriſt alone cleanſeth from all<note n="l" place="margin">1 Iohn 1.7. 1 Cor. 6.11.</note> ſinne.</p>
               <p n="73">73. Queſt. <hi>Why then doeth the holy ghoſt call Baptiſme the waſhing of the new birth, and forgivenes of ſinnes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> God ſpeaketh ſo not without great cauſe; to wit, not onely to teach vs, that as the filth of our body is purged by water, ſo our ſinnes alſo are<note n="m" place="margin">Apoc. 1.5. 1 Cor. 6.11.</note> purged by the bloode and ſpirit of Chriſt: but much more to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as by this divine token and pledge, that we are as verily waſhed from our ſins with the inward waſhing, as we are<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 16.16. Gal. 3.17.</note> waſhed by the outward and viſible water.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Are infants to be baptiſed alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> What elſe: For ſeeing they<note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 17.7.</note> belong as wel vnto the covenant &amp; church of God, as they who are of a full age, &amp; ſeeing alſo
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:180955:13"/>vnto them is promiſed<note n="“" place="margin">Mat. 19.14</note> remiſſion of ſins by the blood of Chriſt, and the<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 1.14. Pſal. 22.11. Act. 2.39.</note> holy ghoſt the worker of faith, as well as vnto thoſe of full growth. They are by baptiſme to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted into the Church of God, and to be † diſcerned from the children of infidels,<note place="margin">Act. 10.47.</note> in like ſorte as in the olde Teſtament was done by<note n="“" place="margin">Gen. 17.14</note> circumciſion, in place whereof<note n="*" place="margin">Coloſ. 2.11.12.13.</note> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme ſucceeded in the new Teſtament.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>OF THE LORDS SVPPER.</head>
               <p n="75">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>28</label> 75. Queſt. <hi>How art thou in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per admoniſhed and waranted, that thou art partaker of that onely ſacrifice of Christ of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered partaker of that onely ſacrifice of Christ of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered on the Croſſe, and of all his benefites?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt hath commaunded me and all the faithfull, to eat of this bread broken, and to drink of the cup diſtributed in remembrance of him, with this promiſe<note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 26.27. Mar 14.22. Luke 22.16. 1 Cor. 10.16.</note> adioyned: Firſt, that his body was as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainlie broken and offered for me on the Croſſe, &amp; his blood ſhed for me, as I behold with my eies the bread of the Lord broken vnto me, and the cup communicated to me: and further, that my ſoule is no leſſe aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly fed to everlaſting life with his body, which was crucified for vs, and his blood, which was ſhed for vs; than I receive &amp; taſte by the mouth of my body the bread and wine, the ſignes of the body and blood of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:180955:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>our Lord, received at the hand of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               <p n="76">76. Queſt. <hi>What is it to eate the body of Christ crucified, and to drinke his blood that was ſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is not only to imbrace by an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red confidence of mind, the whole paſſion and death of Chriſt, and there by to<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 6.35.40.47.48.</note> obtaine forgivenes of ſinnes and everlaſting life, but alſo by the holy ghoſt, who dwelleth both in Chriſt and vs, ſo more and more to bee<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 6.56.</note> vnited to his ſacred body, that though hee be in<note n="c" place="margin">Acts 3.21. 1 Cor. 11.26.</note> heaven, and we in earth, yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les are we fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his<note n="d" place="margin">Ephe. 5.29. 1 Cor. 6.15. 1 Iohn 3.24.</note> bones; and as all the members of the body are by one ſoule, ſo are we alſo quickened and<note n="e" place="margin">Iohn 6.56. Ephe. 4.15.</note> guided by one and the ſame ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="77">77. Queſt. <hi>Where hath Christ promiſed that hee will as certainly give his body and bloud ſo to be eaten and drunken, as they eat this bread broken, and drinke this cup?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the inſtitution of his Supper, the wordes whereof are theſe:<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.23 Mat 26.26. Mar. 14.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in the night that he was betraied, tooke bread: and when he had given thankes, hee brake it, and ſaid, Take, eat, this is my body which is broken for you: this doe you in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me. Likewiſe alſo be tooke the cup when he had ſupped, &amp; ſaid,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Exod. 24.8. Heb. 9.20.</note> 
                  <hi>This cup
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:180955:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>is the new Teſtament in my bloud:</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Exod. 13.9.</note> 
                  <hi>this doe as often as ye ſhall drinke it, in remembrance of me. For as often as ye ſhall eat this bread, and drinke this cup, ye ſhew the Lords death till hee come.</hi> This promiſe is repeated by Saint Paul whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith: <hi>The cup of thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, wherewith we give thankes, is it not the communion of the bloud of Christ? The bread which we breake, is it not the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the body of Christ?</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>For we that are many, are one bread and one body, becauſe we all are partakers of one bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="78">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>29</label> 78. Queſt. <hi>Are then the bread and wine made the very body and blood of Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> No verily. But as the water of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is<note n="“" place="margin">Mat. 26.29 Mar. 14.24.</note> not turned into the bloud of Chriſt, but is only a ſigne &amp; pledge of thoſe things that are ſealed to vs in baptiſme: ſo neither is the bread of the Lords ſupper the very body of<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 10 16 &amp;c. and 11.26</note> Chriſt: Although according to the maner of Sacraments, &amp; that<note n="†" place="margin">Gen. 17.10. Exod. 26.27. Acts 7.8. Levit. 16.10.</note> forme of ſpeaking of them which is vſuall vnto the holy Ghoſt, the bread is called the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="79">79 Queſt. <hi>Why then doth Christ call bread his body, &amp; the cup his bloud, or the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in his bloud: and Paul alſo calleth bread and wine, the communion of the body and bloud of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:180955:15"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Chriſt not without great conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſpeaketh ſo: to wit, not onely for to teach vs, that as the bread and wine ſuſtaine the life of the body, ſo alſo his crucified body and bloudſhed are in deed the meat and drink of the ſoule, whereby it is<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 6.51.55.56.</note> nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed to eternall life: but much more, that by this viſible ſigne and pledge hee may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs, that wee are as verily partakers of his body and bloud, through the working of the holy ghoſt, as we doe<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.6.</note> receive by the mouth of our body theſe holy ſignes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him: and further alſo, that his ſuffering and obedience is ſo certainlie ours, as though we our ſelves had ſuffered puniſhment for our ſinnes, and had ſatisfied God.</p>
               <p n="80">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>30</label> 80. Queſt. <hi>What difference is there betwene the ſupper of the Lord, &amp; the popiſh Maſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Supper of the Lord teſtifieth to vs that we have perfect forgivenes of all our ſins for that only ſacrifice of Chriſt, which him ſelf once fully<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 7.27. &amp; 9.12.26. Mat 26.28. Luke 22.19.</note> wrought on the croſſe: Then alſo that wee by the holy Ghoſt are graffed into Chriſt, who now according to his humane nature is onely in heaven at the right hand of his<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.17. &amp; 10.16.</note> Father, and there will be<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 1.3. &amp; 8.1, &amp;c.</note> worſhipped of vs, But in the Maſſe it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, that the quick and the dead have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion<note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 4.21. Col. 3.1. Phil. 3.10.</note>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:180955:15"/>of ſins for the only paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, except alſo Chriſt be daily offered of them by their ſacrificers. Further alſo it is taught, that Chriſt is bodily vnder the forme of bread and wine, and therefore is to be<note n="a" place="margin">In canon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Miſſae: item de conſecrat. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. 2.</note> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in them. And ſo the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Maſſe is nothing els than an vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deniall of that only ſacrifice and paſſion of Chriſt Ieſus, and an accurſed idolatrie.</p>
               <p n="81">81. Queſt. <hi>Who are to come vnto the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> They only who are truely ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that they have offended God by their ſins; and yet truſt that thoſe ſins are pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them for Chriſtes ſake: and what other infirmitie they have, that thoſe are covered by his paſſion &amp; death, who alſo deſire more and more to goe forward in faith and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of life. But hypocrites, and they who doe not trulie repent, doe eate and<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and 11.28.</note> drinke damnation to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="82">82. Queſt. <hi>Are they alſo to bee admitted to this ſupper, who in confeſſion and life declare them ſelves to be infidels and vngodly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> No. For by that meanes the covenant of God is profaned, and the wrath of God is<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.21. Iſa. 1.11. Ierem. 7.21.</note> ſtirred vp againſt the whole aſſemblie. Wherefore the Church by the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, vſing the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:180955:16"/>keies of the kingdome of heaven, ought to drive them from this ſupper, till they ſhall repent and change their manners.</p>
               <p n="83">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>31</label> 83. Queſt. <hi>What are the keies of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Preaching of the Goſpell, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall diſcipline: by which heaven is opened to the beleevers: &amp; is<note n="“" place="margin">Mat. 16.19. &amp; 18.18.</note> ſhut againſt the vnbeleevers.</p>
               <p n="84">84. Queſt, <hi>How is the kingdome of heaven opened &amp; ſhut by the preaching of the goſpell?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> When by the commaundement of Chriſt it is publiklie declared to all &amp; every one of the faithfull, that all their ſinnes are pardoned them of God, for the merite of Chriſt, ſo often as they imbrace by a lively faith the promiſe of the Goſpell: but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily is denounced to all infidels and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, that ſo long the wrath of God and everlaſting damnation doth lie on them, as they<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 20.21.22.2.3. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 16.19.</note> perſiſt in their wickednes: according to which teſtimonie of the Goſpell, God will iudge them as well in this life, as in the life to come.</p>
               <p n="85">85. Queſt. <hi>How is the kingdome of heaven opened and ſhut, by Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> When according to the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt, they who in name are chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but in their doctrine and life, ſhewe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:180955:16"/>them ſelves<note n="“" place="margin">Rom. 11.7.8.9. 1 Cor. 12 28.</note> aliens from Chriſt, after they having been ſometime admoniſhed, will not depart from their errors or wickednes, are made knowen vnto the Church, or to them that are appointed for that matter, &amp; purpoſe of the Church: and if neither then they obey their admonition, are of the ſame men by interdiction from the Sacramentes ſhutt out from the Congregation of the Church, and by God him ſelfe, out of the kingdome of heaven: And againe, if they profeſſe and in deed declare amendment of life, are<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 18.15. 1 Cor. 5.3.4. 2 Theſ. 3.14. 1 Tim. 5.17.</note> receyved as members of Chriſt and his Church.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>THE THIRD PART, OF MANS THANKFVLNES.</head>
            <p n="86">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>32</label> 86. Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When as we are delivered from all our ſins and miſeries without any merit of ours, by the mercie of God only for Christes ſake: for what cauſe are we to doe good workes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEcauſe, after that Chriſt hath redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs with his bloud, hee renueth vs alſo by his ſpirit to the image of himſelfe: that we receiving ſo great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, ſhould ſhewe our ſelves all our life
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:180955:17"/>time<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.13. &amp; 12.1.2. 1 Pet. 2.5.</note> Thankfull to God, and<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 5.16. 1 Per. 2.12.</note> honor him. Secondly, that everie of vs may be<note n="c" place="margin">2. Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.10. Gal. 5.6.</note> aſſured of his faith, by his fruit. And laſtly, that by our honeſt and good converſation, we may<note n="d" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.1. 2 Matt. 5.16. Rom. 14.19.</note> winne others vnto Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="87">87. Queſt. <hi>Can not they then bee ſaved, which be vnthankefull, &amp; remaine ſtill care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſlie in their ſinnes, and are not converted from their wickednes vnto God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By no meanes. For, as the ſcripture beareth witnes, neither vnchaſt perſons, nor Idolaters, nor adulterers, nor theeves, nor covetous men, nor drunkards, nor ſlaunderers, nor robbers, ſhall<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.9. Ephe. 5.5. 1 Iohn 3.14.</note> enter into the kingdome of God.</p>
            <p n="88">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>33</label> 88. Queſt. <hi>Of what partes conſisteth the converſion of men vnto God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It conſiſteth of the<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 6.4. Ephe. 4.22. Col. 3.5. 1 Cor. 5.7.</note> mortifying of the old man, and the quickning of the new man.</p>
            <p n="89">89. Queſt. <hi>What is the mortifying of the old man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To be truly and hartily ſorry, that thou haſt offended God by thy ſinnes, and daily more and more to hate &amp;<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 8.13. Ioel. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>13.</note> eſchew them.</p>
            <p n="90">90. Queſt. <hi>What is the quickening of the new man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> True ioy in God through<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 5.1. &amp; 14.17 Iſa. 57.15.</note> Chriſt,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:180955:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>and an earneſt and readie deſire to order thy life according to Gods will, and to doe<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.10. Gal. 2.20.</note> all good workes.</p>
            <p n="91">91. Queſt. <hi>What are good workes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thoſe onely which are done by a true<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 14.23</note> faith, according to<note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22 Ephe. 2.10.</note> Gods lawe, and<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> are referred only to his glorie: and not thoſe which are imagined by vs, as ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to vs to be right and good, or which are<note n="e" place="margin">Deut. 11.32. Eze. 20.18. Mat. 15.9.</note> delivered and commanded by men.</p>
            <p n="92">92. Queſt. <hi>Which is the Law of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> God ſpake all<note n="f" place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.1.2.3 Deut. 5.6.7.</note> theſe wordes:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>I am the Lord thy God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exe 20</note> 
                  <hi>which hath brought thee out of Aegypt, out of the houſe of bondage, thou ſhalt have no other gods in my ſight.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Thou ſhalt make to thee no graven Image, nor the likenes of any thing that is in heaven above, or in the earth beneath, nor in the water vnder the earth. Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, nor worſhip them: for I the Lord thy God, am a ielous God, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the children vnto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, and ſhewe mercy vnto thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes of them that love me, and keepe my commaundements.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine: for the Lord will
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:180955:18"/>not hold him guiltles that taketh his name in vaine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4.<note place="margin">Deu. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Remember thou keepe holy the Sabboth daye, ſix dayes ſhalt thou labour and doe all, that thou hast to doe, but the ſeaventh day is the Sabboth of the Lord thy God, in it thou ſhalt doe no manner of workes, thou, and thy ſonne, and thy daughter, thy man ſervant, and thy maid-ſervant, thy cattell, and the ſtranger that is within thy gate. For in ſixe dayes the Lord made heaven and earth, the ſea, and all that in them is, and reasted the ſeaventh day: Wherefore the Lord bleſſed the ſeaventh day, and hallowed it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother,</hi>
                  <hi>that thy dayes may bee longe in the lande, which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>Thou ſhalt doe no murther.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>Thou ſhhalt not commit adulterie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. <hi>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thy neighbour.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy neighbours houſe, nor his wife, nor his ſervant, nor his maid, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe, nor any thing that is his.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="93">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sun. </seg>34</label> 93. Queſt. <hi>How are the commaundements devided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Into two<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 34.28 Deut. 4.13. &amp; 10.34.</note> tables, whereof the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:180955:18"/>delivereth in foure commaundements, how wee ought to behave our ſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes God: The latter delivereth in ſix commanndements, what duties wee <hi rend="sup">a</hi> owe vnto our neighbour.</p>
            <p n="94">94. Queſt. <hi>What doeth God require in the first commaundement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That, as dearelie as I render the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of my owne ſoule, ſo earneſtlie ſhould I ſhunne and flie all<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor 6.9.10 &amp; 10.7.14</note> Idolatrie, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie, enchantements,<note n="d" place="margin">Levi. 19.31. Deut. 18.21.</note> ſuperſtition, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſaints, or anie other<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 4.12. Apo. 19.10.</note> creatures: and ſhould rightlie<note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 17.3.</note> acknowledge the only and true God<note n="g" place="margin">Iere. 17.5.</note>, truſt in him alone,<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 10.36. Col. 1.11. Rom. 5.3.4. Phil. 2.14.</note> ſubmitt and ſubiect my ſelf vnto him with all<note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>5.6.</note> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie and patience,<note n="k" place="margin">Pſa. 104.27. Iſa. 45.7. Iac. 1.17.</note> looke for all good things from him alone, and laſtly, with the entire affection of my heart<note n="l" place="margin">Deut. 6.5. Mat. 22.37.</note> love,<note n="m" place="margin">Deut. 6. Mat 10.28.</note> reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 4.20. Deut. 10.20.</note> worſhip him: ſo that I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to renounce and forſake all creatures rather, then to<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 5.29.</note> commit the leaſt thinge that may be againſt his will.</p>
            <p n="95">95. Queſt. <hi>What is Jdolatrie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is, in place of that one God, or beſides that one and true God, who hath manifeſted him ſelfe in his worde, to make or imagine, and account any other thing, wherein thou repoſeſt thy<note n="p" place="margin">1 Para. 16. Phil. 3.19. Gal. 4.8. Ephe. 2.12.</note> hope and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</p>
            <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 22.37.38.39.</note>
            <p n="96">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:180955:19"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>34</label> 96. Queſt. <hi>What doeth the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement require?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That we ſhould not<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 4.15. Iſa. 40.18. Rom. 1. Acts 17.19.</note> expreſſe or repreſent God by any image, or ſhape and figure, or<note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 15. Deut. 12.30.</note> worſhip him any otherwiſe than he hath commaunded in his word him ſelfe to be worſhipped.</p>
            <p n="97">97. Queſt. <hi>May there then at all any i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages or reſemblances of things be made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> God neither ought nor can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by any meanes: and for the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, although it bee lawfull to expreſſe them, yet God forbiddeth notwithſtanding their images to be made or had, as thereby to worſhip or<note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 23.24 &amp; 34.13.14. Num. 33.52. Deut. 7.5.</note> honor either them, or God by them.</p>
            <p n="98">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>35</label> 98. Queſt. <hi>But may not images bee tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in Churches, whiche may ſerve for bookes vnto the common people?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No. For it is not ſeemely that wee ſhould be wiſer than God, who will have his Church to be<note n="d" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16. 2 Pet. 1.19.</note> taught with the livelie preaching of his word, and not with dum be<note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 10.8. &amp;c Hab. 2.18.19.</note> images.</p>
            <p n="99">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sun. </seg>36</label> 99. Queſt. <hi>What doeth God decree in the third commaundement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That not only by curſing, or<note n="f" place="margin">Lev. 24.11. and 19.2.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing, but alſo by<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 5.37. Iac. 5.12.</note> raſh ſwearing wee
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:180955:19"/>ſhould not vſe his name deſpitefully or vnreverently: neither ſhould by ſilence or connivence be pertakers of thoſe horrible ſinnes in others.: But that wee<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 45.4.</note> vſe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and holy name of God ever with great devotion and reverence: that hee may bee<note n="i" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.8.</note> worſhipped and honoured by vs with a true and ſtedfaſt<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 2.24. 1 Tim. 6.1. Col. 3.16.17.</note> confeſſion, and<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 10.32.</note> invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his name: and laſtly in all our words and actions whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="100">100. Queſt. <hi>Js it then ſo grievous a ſinne by ſwearing or banning, to take the name of God in vaine, as that God is alſo angrie with them, who, as much as in them lieth, doe not forbid or hinder it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Surely moſt<note n="m" place="margin">Levit. 5.1.</note> grievous. For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there anie ſinne greater, or more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending God, than the deſpiting of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred name. Wherefore alſo he<note n="n" place="margin">Lev. 24.15.</note> would have this ſinne to be puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="101">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>37</label> 101. Queſt. <hi>May a man ſweare alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſlie and lawfully by the name of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> He may: when as either the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate exacteth it, or otherwiſe neceſſitie requireth by this meanes the faith &amp; truth of anie man or thing to be ratified and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed: whereby both the glorie of God may be advanced, and the ſafetie of others procured. For this kinde of ſwearing is
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:180955:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Deut 6.13. Heb. 6.16.</note> ordained by Gods worde, and therefore was well<note n="p" place="margin">Gen. 21.24. Ioſ. 5.15.19. 1 Sam. 24.22.</note> vſed of the Fathers both in the old, and new Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="102">102. Queſt. <hi>Is it lawfull to ſweare by Saints, or other creatures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No: For a lawfull oath is an invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of God,<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u. 20. &amp; 17.10 &amp; 20.12. Pſal. 7.9. Reu. 2.13.</note> whereby we deſire, that he, as the only ſearcher of hearts, beare witnes vnto the trueth, and puniſh the ſwearer, if he wittingly<note n="q" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.23.</note> ſweare falſlie. But this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 5.34.35</note> agreeth to no creature.</p>
            <p n="103">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>38</label> 103. Queſt. <hi>What doeth God commaund in the fourth commaundement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, that the miniſterie of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and the ſchooles of learning ſhould be<note n="ſ" place="margin">Fit. 1.15. 1 Tim. 3.14. 1 Cor. 9.11. 2 Tim. 1.2.</note> maintained: and that I, eſpecially on the Sabboth,<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 86.26. and 40.9.10. Acts 2.42.46.</note> frequent ſtudiouſlie divine aſſemblies:<note n="v" place="margin">1 Cor. 14 19 29.31.</note> heare the word of God dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie; vſe the<note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.33</note> Sacramentes:<note n="y" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.1.2.3.8.9. 1 Cor. 14.16.</note> ioyne my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with the common prayers of the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie: and beſtow ſomething according to my abilitie,<note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 26.</note> on the poore. And further, that all my life time I be free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſdeedes and evill actions, yeelding vnto the Lord, that he may by his holy ſpirit worke in me his worke: and ſo I may<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 66.23.</note> begin in this life that everlaſting Sabboth.</p>
            <p n="104">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>39</label> 104. Queſt. <hi>What doeth God enioine vs in the ſift commaundement?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:180955:20"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That we yeeld due honor, love, and faithfulneſſe to our Parentes, and ſo to all, who beare rule over vs, and<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 6.1.2. &amp;c Col. 3.18. Ephe. 5.2. Rom. 13.1.</note> ſubmit our ſelves with ſuch obedience, as is meete, to their faithfull commandementes, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſementes: And further alſo, that by our patience we<note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 23.21. 1 Pet. 2.18.</note> beare and ſuffer their vices &amp; maners, ever thinking with our ſelves, that God will<note n="c" place="margin">Ephe 6.4.9. Col. 3.19.21. Rom. 13. Mat. 22.27.</note> governe and guide vs by their hande.</p>
            <p n="105">105. Queſt. <hi>VVhat doeth God exact in the ſixt commaundement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That neither in thought, nor in geſture, much leſſe indeed, I reproch or hate, or harme, or<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 5.12. Gen. 9.6. Mat. 26.52.</note> kill my neighbour, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by my ſelfe, or by another: but<note n="e" place="margin">Ephe. 4.26. Rom. 12.19. Mat. 5.25.</note> caſt away all deſire of revenge. Furthermore, that I<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 13.14. Col. 2.23.</note> hurt not my ſelfe, or caſt my ſelfe wittinglie into any daunger. Wherefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that murthers might not bee commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he hath<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 9.6. Mat. 26.52. Rom. 13.4.</note> armed the Magiſtrate with the ſworde.</p>
            <p n="106">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>40</label> 106. Queſt. <hi>But this commaundement ſeemeth to forbidde murther only?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But in forbidding murther, God doeth further teach that hee hateth the roote and cauſe of murther, to witt,<note n="h" place="margin">Iae 1.20. Gal. 5.20.</note> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 1.29.</note> envie,<note n="k" place="margin">1 Iohn 2.9.</note> hatred, and deſire of revenge, and doeth<note n="l" place="margin">1 Iohn 3.15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> account them all for murther.</p>
            <p n="107">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:180955:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> 107. Queſt. <hi>Is it enough then, that wee kill no man in ſuch ſorte as hath bene ſaid?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is not enough: For when God condemneth anger, envy, hatred, he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that we<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 22.39. &amp; 1.12.</note> love our neighbour as our ſelves, and that wee vſe<note n="n" place="margin">Rom 12.10</note> humanitie, leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, courteſie,<note n="o" place="margin">Ephe. 4.2. Gal. 6.1.2. Mat. 5.5. Rom. 12.18.</note> patience, and<note n="p" place="margin">Exod. 23.5.</note> mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, and<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 5.45.</note> turne away from him, as much as we may, whatſoever may be hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto him. In a word, that we bee ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in minde, as that wee<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 12.20</note> ſticke not to doe good alſo vnto our enemies.</p>
            <p n="108">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>41</label> 108. Queſt. <hi>What is the meaning of the ſeaventh commaundement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That God hath in<note n="ſ" place="margin">Lev. 18.27.</note> execration, all turpitude, and filthines, and therefore wee alſo muſt<note n="t" place="margin">Iud. 22.13.</note> vtterlie hate and deteſt it, and contrariwiſe live temperately, modeſtly, &amp;<note n="v" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.3.</note> chaſtlie, whether wee<note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 13.4. 1 Cor. 7.4.</note> live in holy wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, or in ſingle life.</p>
            <p n="109">109. Queſt. <hi>Forbiddeth God nothing els in this commaundement, but adulterie, and ſuch kindes of vncleannes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Seeing both our body and ſoule are the temples of the holy ghoſt,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.16. &amp; 6.19. 2 Cor. 6.16.</note> God will have vs to poſſeſſe both in puritie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines. And therefore deedes, geſtures,<note n="y" place="margin">Ephe. 5.3. 1 Cor. 6.18.</note> wordes, thoughts,<note n="z" place="margin">Mat. 5.27.</note> filthy luſtes, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever entiſeth a man vnto theſe, all that
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:180955:21"/>he wholy<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 5.18. 1 Cor. 15.33.</note> forbiddeth.</p>
            <p n="110">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sun. </seg>42</label> 110. Queſt. <hi>What doeth God forbid in the eight commaundement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not only thoſe<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.10.</note> theftes, and<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.10.</note> rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries which the Magiſtrate puniſheth: but by the name of theft, hee comprehendeth whatſoever evill craftes, fetches and deviſes, whereby we ſeeke after other mens goods, and endevour by force, or with ſome ſhew of right, to<note n="d" place="margin">Luc. 3.14. 1 Theſ. 4.6.</note> convey them over vnto our ſelves: of which ſorte are; falſe<note n="e" place="margin">Pro. 11.1.</note> weights, falſe elns, vneven<note n="f" place="margin">Ezec. 45.9. Deut. 25.13.</note> meaſures, deceitfull mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, counterfeit coine,<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 15.5. Luc. 6.35.</note> vſurie, or anie other way or meanes of furthering our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, which God hath forbidden. To theſe we may add all<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.10.</note> covetouſnes: and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold waſt and abuſing of Gods giftes.</p>
            <p n="111">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>43</label> 111. Queſt. <hi>What are thoſe things, which God here commaundeth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That to my power I helpe and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the commodities and profit of my neighbour: and that I ſo deale with him, as I would<note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 5.16.</note> deſire to bee dealth with my ſelfe: and that I doe my own work painfully, and faithfully, that I<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 7.12.</note> may thereby helpe others alſo who are diſtreſſed with any neede or calamitie.</p>
            <p n="112">112. Queſt. <hi>What doeth the ninth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement exact?</hi>
            </p>
            <note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 10.27. ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 12.31.</note>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:180955:22"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That I beare no falſe<note n="l" place="margin">Pro. 19.5.6. and 21.28.</note> witnes againſt any man, neither<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 13.3.</note> falſifie any mans words, neither backbite or<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 1.29.</note> reproch anie man, nor<note n="o" place="margin">Ma. 7.1. &amp;c. Luke. 6.37.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne anie man raſhly or vnheard, but avoid and<note n="p" place="margin">Iohn 8.44.</note> ſhunne with all carefulneſſe all kinde of lies, and deceipt, as the<note n="q" place="margin">Pro. 12.22. &amp; 13.5.</note> proper works of the divell: except I meane to ſtirre vp againſt me the moſt greevous wrath of God. And that in iudgements and other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires I follow the trueth, and freelie and conſtantly<note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.6. Ephe 4 25.</note> profeſſe the matter as it in deed is: And moreover defend and<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> encreaſe, as much as in me lieth, the good name and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation of others.</p>
            <p n="113">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>44</label> 113. Queſt. <hi>What doeth the tenth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement forbid?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That our hearts be not at any time moved by the leaſt deſire, or cogitation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt anie commaundement of God: but that continuallie and from our heart, we deteſt all ſinne, and contrarily,<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 7.7 &amp;c</note> delight in all righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p n="114">114. Queſt. <hi>But can they, who are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto God, perfectlie obſerve and keepe theſe commaundements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No: But even the holieſt men as long as they live, have onely ſmall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of this<note n="v" place="margin">Rom. 7.14.</note> obedience: yet ſo, that they<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 7.22. Iac. 2.10.</note> begin with an earneſt and vnfained deſire
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:180955:22"/>&amp; endeavour to live not according to ſome onelie, but according to all the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God.</p>
            <p n="115">115. Queſt. <hi>Why will God then have his Law to bee ſo exactlie and ſeverely preached, ſeeing there is no man in this life, who is able to keepe it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, that all our life time we more &amp; more<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 1.9. Pſal. 22.5.</note> acknowledge the great pronenes of our nature to ſinne, and ſo much the more greedily<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> deſire remiſſion of ſinnes, &amp; righteouſnes in Chriſt: Secondly, that wee be<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.24. Phil. 3.12.13.14.</note> doing of this alwaies: and alwaies thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of that, and implore and crave of the Father the grace of his holy ſpirit, whereby we may daily more and more bee renued to the image and likeneſſe of God, vntill at length after wee are departed out of this life, we may ioyfully attaine vnto that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which is propoſed vnto vs.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>OF PRAYER.</head>
               <p n="116">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>45</label> 116. Queſt. <hi>Wherefore is Prayer neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for Christians?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe it is the chief part of that<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> thankfulnes which God requireth of vs. And alſo becauſe God giveth them onely his grace and holy ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.26.</note> who with vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned gronings, begge them continually of him, and<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 7.7.1. Luk. 11.9.13. Mar. 13.12.</note> yeeld him thankes for them.</p>
               <p n="117">
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:180955:23"/> 117. Queſt. <hi>What is required vnto that prayer, which ſhall pleaſe God, and bee heard of him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That we aske of the only true God, who hath<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 4.22.</note> manifeſted him ſelfe in his word, all things, which he hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 8.26. 1 Iohn. 5.14.</note> asked of him with a true affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deſire of our heart, and through an inward<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 4.23.24 Pſal. 145.18.</note> feeling of our neede and miſerie<note n="d" place="margin">2 Par. 20.12</note> caſt our ſelves downe proſtrate in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his divine maieſtie: and<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 2.11. &amp; 39. Iſa. 66.2.</note> builde our ſelves on this ſure foundation, that we, though vnworthy, yet for Chriſtes ſake, are certainly<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 10.14. and 8.15.16. Iac. 1.6. &amp;c.</note> heard of God, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he hath<note n="g" place="margin">Io. 14.13. Dan. 9.17.18. Mat. 7.8. Pſal. 133.1.</note> promiſed vs in his word.</p>
               <p n="118">118. Queſt. <hi>What are thoſe thinges, which he commaundeth vs to aske of him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> All<note n="h" place="margin">Iac. 1.17. Mat. 6.33.</note> things neceſſary both for ſoule and body: which our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath compriſed in that prayer, which him ſelfe hath taught vs.</p>
               <p n="119">119. Queſt. <hi>What prayer is that? Anſ.</hi> OVR<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 6.9.10.13 Luc. 11.2. &amp;c. 3.4. Mat. 7.9.</note> Father, which art in heaven, hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed bee thy name; thy kingdome come: thy will be done in earth, as it is in heaven. Give vs this day our daily bread. And forgive vs our treſpaſſes, as wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them that treſpaſſe againſt vs: And lead vs not into temptation: but deliver vs from
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:180955:23"/>evill: for thine is the kingdome, the power, and glorie, for ever, and ever. AMEN.</p>
               <p n="120">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>46</label> 120. Queſt. <hi>Why doeth Christ teach vs to call God our Father?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That preſently in the very entrance and beginning of the prayer, he might ſtirr vp in vs ſuch a reverence and confidence in God, as is meet for the ſons of God, which muſt be the ground and foundation of our prayer: to wit, that God through Chriſt is made our Father, and will much leſſe denie vnto vs thoſe thinges, whiche wee aske of him with a true faith, than our earthly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes<note n="“" place="margin">Mat. 7.9.10.11. Luke 11.11.</note> denie vnto vs earthly things.</p>
               <p n="121">121. Queſt. <hi>Why is that added, which art in heaven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That we<note n="*" place="margin">Ier. 23.24. Acts 17.24.</note> conceive not baſely or terrenely of Gods heavenly Maieſtie: And alſo that wee<note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 10.12.</note> looke for &amp; expect from his omnipotencie, whatſoever things are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for our ſoule and body.<note place="margin">mat 6.9. luk. 11.2</note>
               </p>
               <p n="122">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>47</label> 122. Queſt. <hi>What is the firſt petition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Hallowed be thy name:</hi> that is, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs firſt to<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 17.3. Ier. 9.23.24. Mat. 16.17. Iac. 1.5.</note> know thee aright, and to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, praiſe, and<note n="“" place="margin">Pſal. 119.137.138. Luke 1.46. Pſal. 145.8.9.</note> magnifie thy almighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, goodneſſe, iuſtice, mercie, and trueth ſhyning in all thy works. And further alſo, to direct our whole life, thoughts, words, &amp; workes to this ende, that thy moſt holy
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:180955:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>name be not reproched for vs, but rather be<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 115.1. and 71.8. Mat 6.10</note> renowmed with honour and praiſes.</p>
               <p n="123">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sun. </seg>48</label> 123. Queſt. <hi>What is the ſecond petition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Let thy kingdome come,</hi> that is, rule vs ſo by thy word and ſpirit, that we<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 6.33. Pſal. 119.5.</note> may humble and ſubmit our ſelves more and more vnto thee: preſerve and increaſe thy<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 51.20.</note> Church; deſtroy the workes of the devill, and all power that lifteth vp it ſelfe againſt thy Maieſtie: make all thoſe counſails fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and voide which are<note n="d" place="margin">1 Iohn 3.8. Rom. 16.20.</note> taken againſt thy worde, vntill at length thou<note n="e" place="margin">Apoc. 22.</note> raigne fully and perfectly, when thou ſhalt be all in<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.28</note> all.</p>
               <p n="124">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday </seg>49</label> 124. Queſt. <hi>What is the third petition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Thy will he done in earth, as it is in heaven:</hi> that is, graunt that we and all men renouncing and<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 16.24. Tit. 2.12.</note> forſaking our owne will, may readily and without any<note n="h" place="margin">Luke 22.42</note> grudging obey thy will, which is only holy: and that ſo every of vs may faithfully and cheerfullie<note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.24.</note> performe that duety and charge whiche thou haſt committed vnto vs, even as the bleſſed Angels doe in<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 103.20</note> heaven.</p>
               <p n="125">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>50</label> 125. Queſt. <hi>What is the fourth petition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Give vs this day our daylie bread:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">mat 6.11 Luk 16.3.</note> that is, give vnto vs all things which are<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 145.15 Mat. 25. &amp;c.</note> needfull for this life, that by them wee may acknowledge and confeſſe thee to bee
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:180955:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>the only fountaine, from whence all good things<note n="a" place="margin">Acts 17.27.</note> flow, and all our care and induſtrie, and even thine owne giftes to bee vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 53.53 Deut. 8.3. Pſa. 27.16.17</note> noiſome vnto vs, except thou bleſſe them. Wherefore, graunt that tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our truſt away from all creatures, wee<note n="c" place="margin">Pſa. 62.11. and 55.23</note> place and repoſe it in thee alone.</p>
               <p n="126">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>51</label> 126. Queſt. <hi>What is the fift petition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Forgive vs our treſpaſſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 11.4</note>
                  <note place="margin">mat. 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>as wee forgive them that treſpaſſe against vs:</hi> that is, Even for the blood of Chriſt, doe not<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 51.1. 1 Ihon. 2.1.2.</note> impute vnto vs moſt miſerable and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinners, all our offences, neither that corruption, which ſtill cleaveth vnto vs: even as we alſo feele this teſtimonie of thy grace in our heartes, that wee ſtedfaſtlie purpoſe vnfeignedlie from our heart, to<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 6.14.15.</note> pardon and forgive all thoſe, who have offended vs.</p>
               <p n="127">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sunday. </seg>52</label> 127. Queſt. <hi>What is the ſixt petition?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 11.4</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Lead vs not into temptation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">mat. 6.13.</note> 
                  <hi>but deliver vs from evill:</hi> that is, becauſe wee our ſelves are ſo feeble and weake by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that we<note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 15.51. Pſal. 103.14</note> cannot ſtand ſo much as one moment or inſtant; and our moſt deadlie enemies,<note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.1. Ephe 6.12.</note> ſatan, the<note n="h" place="margin">Iohn 15.1.</note> world, and our own<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 7.23. Gal. 5.17.</note> fleſh, doe inſtantly oppugne and aſſault vs: vphold thou vs, and eſtabliſh &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vs by the might of thy ſpirit, that wee
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:180955:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>may not in this ſpirituall combat<note n="k" place="margin">Mar. 26.41 Mar. 13.33.</note> yeelde as vanquiſhed, but may ſo long ſtoutlie withſtand them, vntill at length wee<note n="l" place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.13. and 5.23.</note> gett the full and perfect victorie.</p>
               <p n="128">128. Queſt. <hi>How concludest thou this prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. For thine is the kingdome, the power, and the glorie, for ever,</hi> that is, we aske and crave all theſe thinges of thee, becauſe, ſeeing both thou art our King, and art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie; thou art both willing and able to<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 10.11 2 Pet. 2.9.</note> give them all vnto vs. And theſe things we therefore aske, that out of them, not to vs, but vnto thy holy Name, all glorie may<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 14.13. Pſal. 115.1. Ier. 33.8.9.</note> redound.</p>
               <p n="129">129. Queſt. <hi>What meaneth this particle, Amen?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That the thing is ſure and out of doubt. For my prayer is much more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly heard of God, than I feele in my hart, that I vnfaignedly<note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tim. 2.13.</note> deſire the ſame.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:180955:25"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:180955:26"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:180955:26"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
